Register of the Hernán Cubillos Sallato papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Hernán Cubillos Sallato papers
1923-2009
92016
Hoover Institution Archives
19 manuscript boxes, 2 oversized boxes (9.8 linear feet)
The papers of Hernán Cubillos Sallato document several aspects of the Pinochet era in Chilean politics. Cubillos Sallato's tenure as Chilean foreign minister included negotiations between Argentina and Chile after a severe dispute developed between the two countries over the Beagle Channel. An end to the conflict, which verged at times on warfare, was mediated by Pope John Paul II. Cubillo Sallato's position as cabinet minister meant that he was also near the center of decision making on other matters under Pinochet, including the wholesale adoption of free market economic principles. He also played a key role as manager of El Mercurio and all its holdings during the Allende period.
Cubillos Sallato, Hernán, 1936-2001
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1992.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1936 February 25 Born, Viña del Mar, Chile
1946-1949 Attended Oratory Preparatory School, Bournemouth, England
1953 Attended Escuela Naval "Arturo Prat," Valparaíso, Chile, graduating as a naval officer
1953-1961 Officer, Chilean Navy; traveled extensively, including sailing on the training ship Esmeralda
1962-1974 Served as executive and then president of El Mercurio publishing company, Santiago, Chile Studied journalism at Columbia University; served as Director of the Interamerican Press Association
1978-1980 Served as Foreign Minister of Chile and played a key role in the resolution, with the mediation of the Vatican, of a dispute with Argentina over the Beagle Channel
2001 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers Hernán Cubillos Sallato document several aspects of the Pinochet era in Chilean politics. Cubillos Sallato's tenure as Chilean foreign minister included negotiations between Argentina and Chile after a severe dispute developed between the two countries over the Beagle Channel. An end to the conflict, which verged at times on warfare, was mediated by Pope John Paul II. Cubillos Sallato's position as cabinet minister meant that he was also near the center of decision making on other matters under Pinochet, including the wholesale adoption of free market economic principles. He also played a key role as manager of El Mercurio.
Cubillos Sallato's time as foreign minister is amply documented in the Ministry of Foreign Affairs File, which consists of bound volumes of clippings that are arranged chronologically. These extensive volumes were produced for Cubillos Sallato by foreign ministry staff.
The Speeches and Writings series, while small, documents Cubillos Sallato's views on foreign policy and economics and revisits a number of episodes that defined his government career. The Correspondence includes an important letter to Cubillos Sallato from Milton Friedman, in which Friedman gives his full endorsement to the economic program implemented by Pinochet and his government and highlights the contributions of the so-called "Chicago Boys" (economists trained at the University of Chicago) to that program. The Reports series also contains detailed information on Chilean politics and economic affairs during the Pinochet era and the transition to democracy undertaken in 1989 to 1990.
The Subject File contains materials relating to the above subjects, but some of these paint a more nuanced picture of Cubillos Sallato's views on the Pinochet years. In particular, the materials on the case of Orlando Letelier show that Cubillos Sallato did consider this to be a case involving the assassination of an opponent to Pinochet. The file also contains some background materials on the Beagle Channel dispute.
A fuller picture of the contribution of Cubillos Sallato to the economic policies of the Pinochet government can be found in the Chicago boys and Latin American market reformers collection in the Hoover Institution Archives. This collection also contains sound recordings of interviews with Cubillos Sallato that were originally part of his papers.
Separated Materials
Five sound recordings, including a series of interviews with Cubillos Sallato conducted by William Ratliff and a lecture by Cubillos Sallato, were transferred in 2011 to the Chicago boys and Latin American market reformers collection.
Related Materials
Chicago boys and Latin American market reformers collection, Hoover Institution Archives
William R. Ratliff papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Chilean subject collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Chile--Economic conditions.; Chile--Foreign relations.; Chile--Politics and government--1973-; Statesmen--Chile.
- Biographical File, 1980-1988 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1980-1988 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Program, 1984 (Folder 1: 2)
- Correspondence, 1984-1992 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains letters and enclosures, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Escámez, Alfonso, 1984 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Friedman, Milton, 1992 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Lagos Escobar, Ricardo, 1992 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Pfeffermann, Guy, 1992 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Raisian, John, 1991 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Ratliff, William, 1984-1992 (Folder 1: 8)
    Includes copy of notes on Beagle Channel dispute with Argentina.
- Speeches and Writings, 1980-1991 (Box 1)
  Contains speeches, seminar presentation, transcript of television interview, and notes, arranged chronologically.
  - Speech on foreign affairs, Escuela de Negocios Adolfo Ibañez, Santiago, Chile, 1980 March (Folder 1: 9)
  - "Alguna consecuencias politicas para Iberoamerica por la crisis financiera internacional," seminar presentation, Santander, Spain, 1984 July 2 (Folder 1: 10)
  - "Ideas on Possible Solutions for Latin American Countries, Toward the End of the Twentieth Century,", 1985 (Folder 1: 11)
  - "Vida civica en Chile hacia fines del siglo viente,", 1987 June 12 (Folder 1: 12)
  - "El desafio de votar," speech, 1987 August 13 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Notes on Chilean politics and foreign policy, 1988 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Notes made in preparation for a television interview, 1988 June (Folder 1: 16)
  - Transcript of interview on Chilean television, 1988 June 13 (Folder 1: 15)
  - "Una nueva vision internacional de Chile,", 1991 (Folder 1: 17)
  - "El tratado de paz y amistad de 1984,", 1991 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Notes for lecture, Santiago, Chile, 1991 April 3 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Notes for lecture on Chilean foreign policy, Academia de Guerra Naval, Valparaiso, Chile, 1991 April 18 (Folder 1: 20)
- Ministry of Foreign Affairs file, 1978-1979 (Box 1-3)
  Bound volumes of press clippings relating to Hernán Cubillos Sallato's tenure as Chilean foreign minister compiled by the ministry, arranged chronologically.
  - 1978
    - April-August (Folder 1: 21)
    - September-December (Folder 2: 1)
  - 1979
    - January-March (Folder 2: 2)
    - April-June (Folder 3: 1)
- Reports, 1986-1992 (Box 3)
  Relating to Chilean politics and the Chilean economy. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1986-1987 (Folder 3: 2)
  - 1988 (Folder 3: 3)
  - 1990-1991 (Folder 3: 4)
  - 1992 (Folder 3: 5-6)
- Writings by Others, 1987-1990 (Box 4)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of author.
  - Arriagada Herrera, Genaro, 1987 (Folder 4: 1)
  - Ortiz Quiroga, Luis, 1987 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Ratliff, William, 1989-1990 (Folder 4: 3)
- Subject File, 1980-1993 (Box 4-5)
  Contains clippings, pamphlets, and reports, largely relating to Chile, and arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Abrams, Elliott, 1987 (Folder 4: 4)
  - Beagle Channel (Argentina and Chile), 1989-1993 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Chile, 1980-1992
    - Armed forces, 1983-1989 (Folder 4: 6)
    - Economic policy, 1982-1992 (Folder 4: 7)
    - Education, 1982 (Folder 4: 8)
    - Foreign relations, 1985-1993 (Folder 4: 9)
    - Human rights, 1992 (Folder 4: 18)
    - Police, 1985 (Folder 5: 6)
    - Politics and government, 1980-1992 (Box 4)
      - 1980-1985 (Folder 4: 10)
      - 1987 (Folder 4: 11)
      - 1987-1988 (Folder 4: 12)
      - 1989 (Folder 4: 13)
      - 1992 (Folder 4: 14)
    - Justice Administration, 1982-1988 (Folder 4: 19)
    - Social conditions, 1986-1987 (Folder 4: 15)
    - United States - Foreign relations, 1983-1985 (Folder 5: 9)
  - Friedman, Milton, 1982 (Folder 4: 16)
  - Globalization, 1992 (Folder 4: 17)
  - Landau, George W., 1982 (Folder 5: 1)
  - Latin America, 1987-1992 (Folder 5: 2)
  - Letelier, Orlando, 1987-1988 (Folder 5: 3)
  - Pensions - Latin America, 1981-1992 (Folder 5: 4)
  - Pinochet, Augusto, 1986-1992 (Folder 5: 5)
  - Smith-Pencavel, Louise, 1982 (Folder 5: 7)
  - Theberge, James D., 1988 (Folder 5: 8)
  - United States - Foreign relations - Latin America, 1985 (Folder 5: 10)
  - Vargas Llosa, Mario, 1993 (Folder 5: 11)
- Miscellany, 1980-1992. (Box 5)
  Contains photograph and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Photograph depicting George W. Landau, 1980 (Folder 5: 12)
  - Printed matter, 1980-1992 (Box 5)
    - Election materials, 1985-1989 (Folder 5: 13)
    - Monograph on Chilean legal system under the presidency of Salvador Allende, 1980 (Folder 5: 14)
    - Serial issues and bulletins relating to Chile, 1984-1992 (Folder 5: 15-27)
- 2014 Incremental Materials, 1923-2009 (Boxes 6-21)
  Correspondence, scrapbooks, and clippings.
  - Indice Archivo Rojo 1 (Box-folder 6: 1)
    Other Finding Aids note
    Downloadable PDF file of item inventory, Archivo Rojo 1
    - Correspondence, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 6: 2-4)
    - Correspondence, 1989 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    - Clippings and correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 6: 6-8)
    - Clippings and correspondence, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 7: 1-2)
    - Clippings and correspondence, 1950-1972 (Box-folder 7: 3)
    - Fotografías y artículos de prensa: Visita oficial a Chile del excelentísimo Señor Sunaro Sonoda, Ministerio de R.R.E.E. Japón, 1979 (Box-folder 7: 4-5)
  - Indice Archivo Rojo 2 (Box-folder 7: 6)
    Downloadable PDF file of item inventory, Archivo Rojo 2
    - Memorias, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 7: 7-9)
    - Memorias, 1977-1981 (Box-folder 8: 1-2)
    - Recortes de prensa, 1978 April 15 - June 2 (Box-folder 8: 3-5)
    - Memorias canciller, 1978 (Box-folder 8: 6-7)
    - Memorias, 1986-1990 (Box-folder 9: 1-3)
  - Indice Archivos 3 (Box-folder 9: 4)
    Downloadable PDF file of item inventory, Indice Archivos 3
    - Tomo empastado azul con información de prensa, 1980 January - April 6 (Box-folder 9: 5)
    - Tomo IV empastado azul con información de prensa, 1979 October - December (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - Tomo III empastado azul con información de prensa, 1979 July - September (Box-folder 10: 2)
    - Tomo empastado azul con información de prensa, 1980-1993 (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - Visita de vicepresidente de Costa Rica Rodrigo Altmann Ortiz y Sra. Gabriela Echeverria de Altmann, 1979 (Box-folder 11: 2)
      Contains photo album.
    - Recortes de prensa de visita de vicepresidente de Costa Rica Rodrigo Altmann Ortiz y Sra. Gabriela Echeverria de Altmann, 1979 (Box-folder 11: 3-5)
      Contains scrap book.
    - Album fotos de visita de ministro de R.R.E.E. Uruguay Adolfo Folle Martinez, 1979 (Box-folder 11: 6)
    - Archivo recortes de prensa de visita de ministro de R.R.E.E. Uruguay Adolfo Folle Martinez, 1979 (Box-folder 12: 1)
    - Album fotos de visita de ministro de R.R.E.E. Peru José de la Puente Radbill y Sra., 1978 (Box-folder 12: 2)
    - Archivo recortes de prensa visita ministro de R.R.E.E. Peru José de la Puente Radbill y Sra., 1978 (Box-folder 12: 3)
  - Indice Varios Archivos 4 (Box-folder 12: 4)
    Downloadable PDF file of item inventory, Indice Varios Archivos 4
    - Archivador rojo memorias, 1973 (Box-folder 12: 5-7)
    - Correspondence, 1989-1993 (Box-folder 12: 8)
    - Cubichete writings, 1956 (Box-folder 12: 9)
    - Cubichete clippings, 1956 (Box-folder 12: 10)
    - El club de yates "Viña del Mar,", 1959 (Box-folder 13: 1)
    - Notes, memos, and articles, 1978-1989 (Box-folder 13: 2)
    - Correspondence, 1980-2000 (Box-folder 13: 3)
    - Correspondence and articles, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 13: 4)
    - Writings, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 13: 5-6)
  - Indice Archivos 5 (Box-folder 13: 7)
    Downloadable PDF file of item inventory, Indice Archivos 5
    - Blue scrapbook, 1988-1990 (Box-folder 13: 8)
    - Blue scrapbook, 1960-1988 (Box-folder 13: 9)
    - Blue scrapbook, 1923-1973 (Box-folder 14: 1)
    - Blue scrapbook, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 14: 2)
    - Blue scrapbook, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 15: 1)
    - Blue scrapbook, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 15: 2)
    - Blue scrapbook, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 16: 1)
    - Rendiciones de cuentas, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 16: 2)
    - Sailing team documents, 1986 (Box-folder 16: 3)
    - "Bitacora de un marino" by Angelica Arndt, 1978 (Box-folder 16: 4-5)
    - Photo album, offical visit to Peru, 1978 (Box-folder 17: 1)
  - Indice Archivos 6 (Box-folder 17: 2)
    Downloadable PDF file of item inventory, Indice Archivos 6
    - Miscellaneous materials, "El Mercurio #1,", 1970-1973 (Box-folder 17: 3-5)
    - Miscellaneous materials, "El Mercurio #2,", 1971-1974 (Box-folder 17: 6-7)
    - Miscellaneous materials, "El Mercurio #3,", 1971-1974 (Box-folder 18: 1-3)
    - Photo album, official visit to China, 1978 (Box-folder 18: 4)
    - Correspondence and clippings, 1950-1972 (Box-folder 18: 5)
    - Official documents, 1976-1983 (Box-folder 19: 1)
    - Memos, correspondence, and clippings, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 19: 2)
      Includes one CD with files.
    - Correspondence, 1980-1989 (Box-folder 19: 3)
    - Correspondence and writings, 1990-2009 (Box-folder 19: 4)
    - Correspondence and clippings, 1959-1992 (Box-folder 19: 5)
    - Correspondence and writings, 1973 (Box-folder 19: 6)
    - Spanish newspapers, 1980-2008 (Box 20)
    - Personal scrapbooks, 1950-1954 (Box 21)